<chapter>
  <title>Configuration</title>
  <para>
    LIXA is constituted of two components: client and server. The figure
    below shows a typical configuration with three distinct Application
    Programs and four different Resource Managers.
  </para>
  <figure xml:id="config1">
    <title>Typical LIXA topology</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="LIXA_Configuration_1.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <section>
    <title>Architectural elements</title>
    <para>
      The <command>lixad</command> daemon process can be executed on any
      system: there is no need it is hosted in the same system is hosting
      the Application Programs. The communications between 
      <command>lixac</command> are based on a TCP/IP socket.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <command>lixac</command> library is embedded in the Application
      Programs; the communication between Application Program and
      <command>lixac</command> is based on TX (Transaction Demarcation)
      API, see <citation>TXspec</citation>. The library contains the logic
      of the LIXA Transaction Manager.
    </para>
    <para>
      The communication between the Application Program and the Resource
      Managers depends on Resource Managers configuration: it may be cross
      memory based, TCP/IP based, etc...
      The communication between the <command>lixac</command> library and the
      Resource Manager depends on Resource Manager configuration and must be
      the same used by the Application Program.
    </para>
    <para>
      The communication between <command>lixac</command> and 
      <command>lixad</command> is ever istantiated by the client: the
      server never calls the client.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Configuring the server</title>
    <para>
      The default configuration file is <filename>etc/lixad_conf.xml</filename>
      and is located at the root installation path (i.e.
      <filename>/opt/lixa/etc/lixad_conf.xml</filename>). 
      Below there is a sample configuration file:
      <screen>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;
  &lt;server pid_file="/tmp/lixa/var/run.pid"&gt;
  &lt;listeners&gt;
    &lt;listener domain="AF_INET" address="127.0.0.1" port="3456"/&gt;
    &lt;listener domain="AF_INET" address="0.0.0.0" port="2345"/&gt;
  &lt;/listeners&gt;
  &lt;managers&gt;
    &lt;manager status_file="/tmp/lixa/var/lixad_status1"/&gt;
    &lt;manager status_file="/tmp/lixa/var/lixad_status2"/&gt;
    &lt;manager status_file="/tmp/lixa/var/lixad_status3"/&gt;
  &lt;/managers&gt;
&lt;/server&gt;
      </screen>
      
      The tags and the
      properties of the XML file are described below:
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	<listitem><para>
	    <varname>pid_file</varname>: the file used by the server to store
	    the daemon <acronym>PID</acronym>
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <varname>listener</varname>: the server can activate one or more
	    listeners; most of the times one listener is sufficient, but if
	    you want to listen only on a subset of the address associated to
	    the server you have to configure many
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <varname>domain</varname>: the type of socket must be used to
	    listen for clients. The only allowed type is 
	    <constant>AF_INET</constant>; this may be different in the future
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <varname>address</varname>: the address must be used to listen for
	    clients; the special value <constant>0.0.0.0</constant> means
	    any address
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <varname>port</varname>: the port must be used to listen for
	    clients; it must be a free port (use command 
	    <command>netstat</command> to find out one)
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <varname>manager</varname>: any configured 
	    <emphasis>manager</emphasis> is a server worker and has its own
	    associated thread. The number of manager should be activated 
	    depends on the workload.
	</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
