<chapter>
  <title>Installation</title>
  <para>
    This chapter explains how to download, install, verify the software
    released by LIXA project.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>System requirements</title>
    <para>
      LIXA project is developed on an x86 based Ubuntu 8.04 system; it
      compiles and runs on both <emphasis>server</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>desktop</emphasis> flavors. Installation on a different Linux
      distribution should be quite straightforward; installation on different
      <emphasis>UNIX like</emphasis> would probably need some work.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you successfully installed LIXA on a different system, you might
      publish your experience on the public forum hosted on SourceForge.net 
      and share your results with other users. 
    </para>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Pre-requisites</title>
    </simplesect>
    <para>
      To compile LIXA software the GNU tools are needed: gcc, gmake, libtool.
      Autoconf and automake are used, but should not be necessary if you want
      to install the original tarball.
    </para>
    <para>
      Some <emphasis>libraries (run time and development stuff)</emphasis> are
      necessary too:
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	<listitem><para>libdl</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>libglib</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>libgmodule</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>libgthread</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>libm</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>libpthread</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>libuuid</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>libxml2</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Software download</title>
    <para>
      The LIXA project is hosted on SourceForge.net portal at this URL:
      <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/lixa/">
	<citetitle>http://sourceforge.net/projects/lixa/</citetitle>
      </link>
    </para>
    <para>
      The software is available only as a <emphasis>source code</emphasis>
      tarball; no
      pre-compiled packages are available: you need C development tools
      installed to have success in LIXA installation. It is suggested to 
      download the gzipped tarball from the main page: the last available
      release is generally what you need; you could download a previous release
      if you had a reason to do it.
    </para>
    <para>
      Alternatively you can fetch the source code using a subversion client,
      but you should pay attention many commits on the subversion repositoty
      are intermediate works and can give you partial or broken under
      construction features.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
