<chapter>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <section>
    <title>Why should I use LIXA project?</title>
    <para>
      LIXA project allows you to develop an Application Program that performs
      two phase commit transactions against two ore more Resource Manager.
      Two phase commit is a conceptual protocol designed to 
      <quote>guarantee</quote> <acronym>ACID</acronym> (Atomicity, Consistency,
      Isolation, Durability) transactionality.
      XA specification is not the only two phase commit protocol implementation
      but it is probably the best known and widespread. For detailed
      explanation please refer to <citation>RefModel</citation>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <warning>
    <para>
      The reference model (<citation>RefModel</citation>) technical guide
      available on the <trademark>Open Group</trademark> web site is more
      recent than the XA specification (<citation>XAspec</citation>); an XA+
      specification exists too and the reference model was updated to
      host the concepts necessary for XA+. LIXA project does not implement
      the XA+ specification, but only XA and the following concepts explained 
      in <citation>RefModel</citation> does not apply to LIXA project:
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	<listitem><para>3.1: Superior Node</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>3.1: Subordinate Node</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>3.1: Communication Resrouce Manager (<acronym>CRM</acronym>)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>3.5: Distributed Communication Facilities</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>3.6: Activity between Functional Components Involving Two or More APs</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>3.7: CRM Communication Paradigms with APs</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>3.8: High-level TP Language</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      XA specification was designed to implement the two phase commit protocol
      in the case there is only one Application Program running inside a
      Transaction Monitor and using a Transaction Manager to coordinate any
      number of Resource Managers. XA+ specification was designed to
      implement the two phase commit protocol in the case there are two or
      more Application Programs running inside distinct Transaction Monitors
      and using distinct Transaction Managers to coordinate any number of
      Resource Managers.
    </para>
  </warning>
  <section>
    <title>Transaction Manager and Transaction Monitor</title>
    <para>
      As explained in Appendix A of <citation>RefModel</citation> a 
      Transaction Manager can be though as a subset of a Transaction Monitor.
      Most commercial products tend to merge the features
      in a single bundle; this is good if you need a Transaction Monitor,
      this may be bad if you only need a Transaction Manager.
    </para>
    <para>
      IBM TXSeries<footnote><para>TXSeries is a registered trademark of 
	  IBM corporation</para></footnote> is a Transaction Monitor with an
      integrated Transaction Manager.
      Oracle (BEA) Tuxedo<footnote><para>Tuxedo is a registered trademark of
	  Oracle corporation</para></footnote> is a Transaction Monitor with an
      integrated Transaction Manager.
      JBOSS<footnote><para>JBOSS is a registered trademark of Red Hat
	  corporation</para></footnote> is a <acronym>JEE</acronym>
      (Java Enterprise Edition) application server; it is a Transaction
      Monitor with an integrated Transaction Manager for bytecode based
      applications.
    </para>
    <para>
      BTM (Bitronix JTA Transaction Manager) is a Transaction Manager, but it
      is not a Transaction Monitor and can be used in conjunction with a
      <acronym>JVM</acronym> (Java Virtual Machine) and possibly any
      Transaction Monitor. Unfortunately it is a Java based technology and not
      a native one; in the Java arena there are a few stand-alone Transaction
      Manager, while in the C language arena it is not easy to find out one.
    </para>
    <para>
      LIXA project implement a stand-alone Transaction Manager your 
      Application Program can use in many different ways:
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	<listitem><para>from a C application launched from shell</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>from a C application launched via CGI from a web server</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>from a scripting language application<footnote><para>You must wrap the TX C API to be able to use it from Perl, PHP, Python, Ruby...</para></footnote></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      With the aid of LIXA Transaction Manager potentially any web server can
      be converted in an Application Server with two phase commit support.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>LIXA Architecture</title>
    <para>
      From an architectural point of view, LIXA project adopts an original
      approach: an Application Program links the LIXA client library and
      embeds the Transaction Manager logic. Every Application Program instance
      runs its own Transaction Manager instance, but every Transaction
      Manager instance uses the LIXA server daemon to save and retrieve the
      state of the managed transactions.
      LIXA project was designed to allow massive parallelism and embedding at
      the same time: the parallelism is necessary to accomplish nowadays
      workloads while the embeddable property is necessary to avoid conflicts
      with process and thread management of the potential Transaction
      Monitors.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Project, Projuct, Product</title>
    <para>
      LIXA is a <emphasis>project</emphasis>: a software artifact you can pick
      up to try, use, modify and distribute according to GPL license terms. 
      The project is hosted on 
      <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/lixa/">
	<citetitle>SourceForge</citetitle>
      </link>
      collaborative portal and you can use the portal
      to interact with the author and other users.
      LIXA is not supported because it is not a product: you can use it AS IS
      without any guarantee.
    </para>
    <para>
      A projuct is a software artifact that was a project financed from a
      customer. When a second customer can be interested in the software
      artifact, it is selled again. When the third customer knocks the door,
      the team developed the project starts a new business with a new
      <emphasis>product</emphasis>. But it is a projuct because it was 
      designed and modeled following the first customer needs.
    </para>
    <para>
      In my honest opinion a <emphasis>product</emphasis> is a software 
      artifact with some characteristics:
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	<listitem><para>it is produced by a software factory</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>it is selled by a commercial network</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>it has a team of specialists you can contact to have 
	    support</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>it has a team of specialists can visit and help you 
	    with installation, configuration, problem determination, 
	    etc...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>it is fully documented</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>it is certified to run properly on some documented 
	    hardware and software platforms</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>it has a certified compatibility matrix the customer
	    can use to find oud a valid mix of distinct software components
	    (i.e. different Resource Managers, for a Transaction Manager
	    like LIXA)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>it can be installed, updated and removed from a system
	    using the standard tool of the platform (i.e. dpkg, rpm, pkg,
	    etc....)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>it can be upgraded to a successive version without
	    side effects for the product and/or the hosting system
	</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <important><para>LIXA project is not a product.</para></important>
    </para>
    <para>
      If you were running a business interested in the development of a
      product based on the technology developed by LIXA project you should
      contact the author through       
      <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/lixa/">
	<citetitle>SourceForge</citetitle>
      </link>
      collaborative portal.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>LIXA and X/OPEN CAE specifications</title> 
    <para>
      LIXA project tries to be as compliant as possible with the X/Open CAE
      specifications cited in bibliography. These are the non implemented
      and/or non implementable features.
    </para>
    <simplesect>
      <title>The commit_return Characteristic</title>
      <para>
	As explained in <citation>TXspec</citation> (3.4, 3.8.1) two values
	are available:
	<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	  <listitem><para><constant>TX_COMMIT_COMPLETED
	    </constant></para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para><constant>TX_COMMIT_DECISION_LOGGED
	    </constant></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	LIXA TX API implementation supports only
	<constant>TX_COMMIT_COMPLETED</constant>
	this behavior is allowed by the specification.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>The transaction state element</title>
      <para>
	As explained in <citation>TXspec</citation> (4.2, page 16)
	<function>tx_info()</function> can return three values:
	<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	  <listitem><para><constant>TX_ACTIVE
	    </constant></para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para><constant>TX_TIMEOUT_ROLLBACK_ONLY
	    </constant></para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para><constant>TX_ROLLBACK_ONLY
	    </constant></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      LIXA <function>tx_info()</function> does not return
      <constant>TX_ROLLBACK_ONLY</constant>. This does not hurt the
      X/Open CAE specification.
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>XA -> TX return code mappings</title>
      <para>
	In <citation>TXspec</citation> (Appendix B.4, page 64) it is suggested
	to return the value <constant>TX_ERROR</constant> when the Resource
	Manager returns <constant>XA_RETRY</constant>; this is explained in
	<quote>note 1</quote>. 
      </para>
      <para>
	The LIXA implementation of 
	For <function>tx_commit()</function> and
	<function>tx_rollback()</function> returns 
	<constant>TX_NO_BEGIN</constant> instead of 
	<constant>TX_ERROR</constant> because it seems a more useful 
	information for the Application Program: the transaction has been
	successfully committed/rolled back, but a new transaction can not be
	started
	<footnote><para>The X/Open CAE specification document
	    <quote>suggests</quote> the mapping and it seems there is some
	    flesibility in the suggestions. From a LIXA perspective all this
	    stuff is academic because <constant>TMNOWAIT</constant> is not
	    used by LIXA implementation.</para></footnote>.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
  </section>
</chapter>
