<chapter xml:id="Development_TC">
  <title>Developing C Application Programs with the Transaction Coupling (TC) TX extensions</title>
  <para>
    This chapter explains how you can develop your own C application using the libraries and tools supplied by the LIXA project.
  </para>
  <para>
    The LIXA project ships with some example C programs that you can find in the <filename>/opt/lixa/share/doc/lixa-X.Y.Z/examples</filename> folder after software installation (see <xref linkend="Installation"/>).
  </para>
  <note><para>
    This chapter is focused on the C programming language for the non-standard extensions that has been added to the TX specification to expose some of the XA interface capabilities. All the information supplied in <xref linkend="Development"/> still applies.
  </para></note>
  <section>
    <title>Non-standard TX (Transaction Demarcation) Specification Extensions</title>
    <para>
      The LIXA project provides extensions to the <citation>TXspec</citation>, named Transaction Coupling (TC), which can be used in addition to the standard API when developing distributed Application Programs.
    </para>
    <para>
      The API extensions are easy to use and the following C example briefly explains it:
      <programlisting>
#include &lt;tx.h&gt;
        
/* your includes */
        
int main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    int rc;
        
    if (TX_OK != (rc = tx_open()))
        /* handle error */
        
    if (TX_OK != (rc = tx_begin()))
        /* handle error */
        
    /* do local work against Resource Manager here */
        
    /* suspend the transaction so that work can continue elsewhere */
    if (TX_OK != (rc = tx_end(TX_TMSUSPEND)))
        /* handle error */
        
    /* in another thread or another Application Program work can continue on the same transaction */
    TXINFO txinfo;
    if (TX_OK != (rc = tx_info(&amp;txinfo)))
        /* handle error */
    if (TX_OK != (rc = tx_join(&amp;txinfo.xid)))
        /* handle error */
    if (TX_OK != (rc = tx_end(TX_TMSUCCESS)))
        /* handle error */
        
    /* take up transaction again */
    if (TX_OK != (rc = tx_resume(&amp;txinfo.xid)))
        /* handle error */
        
    /* commit or roll back transaction */
    if (TX_OK != (rc = tx_commit()))
        /* handle errror */
        
    /* shut down */
    tx_close();
}
      </programlisting>
      These are the available C functions:
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem><para>
          <function>tx_end</function>: manage the global transaction with <parameter class="function">flags</parameter>:
          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem><para>
              <parameter>TX_TMSUSPEND</parameter>: suspend the transaction
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>
              <parameter>TX_TMSUCCESS</parameter>: mark the portion of work on the global transaction as successful
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>
              <parameter>TX_TMFAIL</parameter>: mark the portion of work on the global transaction as failed
            </para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          <function>tx_join</function>: join a suspended global transaction and continue work
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          <function>tx_resume</function>: resume a suspended global transaction - <emphasis>only from the thread that suspended the original transaction</emphasis>
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>LIXA library linkage</title>
    <para>
      See <xref linkend="linkage"/>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The first example</title>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>An example with Oracle</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Deployment model of two example applications with Oracle DBMS</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/LIXA_Development_15.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      This example shows how two application programs can take part in the same global transaction when using the same Resource Manager coordinated by the LIXA Transaction Manager. Please make sure that you are comfortable with previous sections and examples before setting this up.
    </para>
    <para>
      The following relates to the figure above:
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem><para>
          <function>Application Program 1</function>: an application developed in C that is able to call functionality exposed by Application Program 2
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          <function>Application Program 2</function>: an application developed in C that is able to fulfil service functionality when called by Application Program 1
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          <function>A1 and B1</function>: includes Resource Manager specific calls during program execution
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          <function>C1</function>: this is any custom protocol developed or used for communication between Application Program 1 and Application Program 2 - <emphasis>it is important to note that to make use of the Transaction Coupling extensions, one would have to share the XID between the programs.</emphasis>
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      This example was developed using the following configuration:
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
        LIXA must be configured to support the Oracle Resource Manager as explained in <xref linkend="Linking_third_party_resource_managers"/>.
      </para>
    </important>
    <section>
      <title>Set the environment variables</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Build the client programs</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Configure the LIXA environment</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Test program execution</title>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>